Guide to the Maxwell Aley Papers MSS 066
Fales Library and Special Collections
Maxwell Aley Papers
1928-1990
1942-1974
Fales Library and Special Collections
Aley, Ruth
Aley, Maxwell
Aley, Maxwell Parkhurst
MSS 066
2.25 Linear Feet in 2 record cartons, 1 card box, and 1 oversize flat box
1 audiocassette
Maxwell Aley (1889-1953) was an American writer, editor, publisher, and literary agent. After graduating from Indiana University, Aley began his career as editor of the "Daily Commercial" in Bangor, Maine. He held numerous positions as an editor at several magazines and publishing companies and eventually joined his wife, Ruth, as partner at the agency she established in New York City. This collection documents Aley's career and the endeavors of the Aley family's literary agency after his death, ranging from 1928 to 1990. Materials include correspondence, manuscripts, contracts, lists, publications, a few photographs, and one audiocassette.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Maxwell Parkhurst Aley in 1997. The accession number associated with this gift is 0.066.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Biographical / Historical
Maxwell Aley, an American writer, editor, publisher, and literary agent, was born September 21, 1889 in Indiana and died July 16, 1953 in New York. Aley grew up in Indiana and attended Indiana University. His first job was in Bangor, Maine at the "Daily Commercial" where he became managing editor in 1915. That same year he married Ruth Emeilie Tracy Parkhurst. They had two children, Maxwell Parkhurst Aley and Robert Jonathan Aley, who would both become partners in the Aley family's literary agency. Aley held numerous positions as an editor at several magazines and publishing companies in Maine and New York, and eventually left Longmans, Green and Company to join his wife, Ruth, as a parter in the agency she had already established. He was a co-founder of the American and International P.E.N. (Poets, Playwrights, Editors, and Novelists) Clubs, and an active member of the Society of Authors' Representatives, the Authors' League, the National Arts Club, and Phi Beta Kappa National Scholastic Honor Society.
Custodial History
Materials were donated to the University of Wyoming American Heritage Center by Ruth Aley in 1991. Maxwell Parkhurst Aley transferred the materials from the University of Wyoming American Heritage Center and donated them to New York University in 1997.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact fales.library@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of materials that document Maxwell Aley's early career as a writer, editor, publisher, and literary agent beginning in 1929 and the business endeavors of the Aley family's literary agency up to 2010. Materials include correspondence, manuscripts, contracts, lists, publications, a few photographs, and one audiocassette.
Literary agents.; Literary editors.; Authors, American -- 20th century.; Authors, American -- 20th century -- Correspondence; Authors and publishers -- New York (State) -- New York -- 20th century.; Editors -- New York (State) -- New York; Correspondence.; Manuscripts (document genre); Photographs.; Publications (documents); Contracts; Aley, Maxwell; Gluck, Jay; Maxwell, Nicole; Aley, Ruth
- New Frontiers in Medicine, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Health '62 - '69, 1962-1966 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Gluck, Zen, 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Burford publicity reviews, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Wyo [sic] make copies, 1939-1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Royalty records: active clients, 1971-1987 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Publicity, 1962-1983 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Ruth Aley: answer, 1956-1988 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1982-1990 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bert Stiles-Bauer [audiocassette], 1983 (Box Shared Fales 006)
- Biographical information, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Williamson Archer, undated (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
- "1990", 1967-1987 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1933-1987 (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
- Bambino Goes West by Andrew S. Wing, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Maria Kuncewicz [sic], 1961-1963 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Jay Gluck, 1956-1962 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Gluck: '63, '64, '65, '66, '67, 1961-1967 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Gluck = J.S.O. [sic] 1969, 1960-1971 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Legal agreements for authors, 1957-1965 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Contracts: Mary Jack Wald, 1946, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Author-agent contracts, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Daisy Newman, 1944-1954 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- B, 1951-1974 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Correspondence and manuscripts, 1942-1948, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Correspondence, 1928-1968 (Box 1, Folder 28-29)
- S, 1944-1972 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Manuscripts, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Partridge, Bellamy, 1952-1958 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Marjorie Holmes, 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Manuscripts, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
- 1971 Log Book, 1971-1981 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- "You're Not Tough" by Maxwell Aley, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Good Housekeeping, 1926-08 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Bert Stiles + [Dan] Baur, 1941-1973 (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
- Riki Stevens, 1987-1989 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Ferguson - Bolt: foreign, England '78, 1973-1978 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Aley, Maxwell, 1927-1939 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Maxwell Aley - autographed letters, 1921-1936 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Maxwell Aley Associates, 1929-1975 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- C. Jonas, 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Maxwell Aley Anthology of War Stories, 1947-1957 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- M. Aley, 1927-1951 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- David Bolt - general, 1985-1989 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Maxwell Aley American biography, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Good Housekeeping, 1927-07 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- N. Sullivan, 1965-1983 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Nicole Maxwell: magazines, 1958-1974 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Nicole Maxwell: publications, etc., 1952-1987 (Box 2, Folder 18-19)
- Stiles, Bert, 1940-1942 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Manuscript page, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Cocannoer, Joseph, 1956-1959 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- J.A. Brown, 1950-1960 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Survey - Gluck, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Maria Kuncewiczowa, 1961-1982 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Ukiya-Gluck, 1962-1968 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Publishers, 1976-1989 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Olema, California, 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Correspondence, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Joe Durso, 1987-1989 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Lists, 1949-1951 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Iran-Gluck, 1960-1963 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Submissions and sales, 1943-1944, undated (Box 2, Folder 33-34)
- Pope [Arthur Upham Pope], 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Gluck, '68, '69, '70, 1961-1972 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Pictorial Review, 1929 (Box Shared Fales 002, Folder 22)